Hi and welcome to step one, mass of the majority of A2 forces and momentum. Now this is a huge
topic. It's almost a little bit overwhelming and it covers three main concepts. It covers forces,
momentum and circular motion. So for that reason I've actually split this tutorial out into three
parts. Part one covers learning objectives one to seven and that's a topic of forces.
Part two covers learning objectives seven to twelve and that's a topic of momentum.
And part three covers learning objectives 13 to 16 and that covers circular motion. In your
revision split these up into three parts to make it a bit more bite-sized and achievable for you
to work through. In step one there are three resources that you need to make sure that you
master the majority and they're downloadable below. You download the learning objective checklist,
the revision note template and the knowledge questions and answers. That's three things you
download. The first thing you do is you go to the learning objectives checklist and you tick
off everything you're good at. You circle the learning objectives that you think you might
struggle with. Then you fast forward this video to the learning objectives that you think you're
struggling with. You watch the video and as you're watching the video you fill out the revision
note template and the knowledge questions and I will help you on every step of the way.
The whole point of step one master the majority is to identify where you're struggling a little
bit with the concepts, teach you those concepts and make sure you can apply those concepts
in specifically written out questions for you. Those questions are not past paper questions,
that's in step two. This is simply to make sure you understand the concepts
and you have a wide range of knowledge covering the whole of the topic. Okay let's go. These
seven learning objectives relate to the forces section of A2 forces and momentum and we'll
discuss these in the following tutorial. We look at Newton's three laws of motion,
how to apply them and then we actually just make sure you understand what each force means
and the formula for each force. So it's a fairly detailed tutorial. Let's start off. We're going
to start by looking at Newton's three laws of motion which is learning objective one and
describing forces as interactions between bodies which is learning objective number four.
You will know from previous study that Newton's laws relate to forces and we can't learn about
Newton's laws unless you understand what a force is and the best way to understand what a force is
is to learn a definition. The definition is a push or a pull that acts upon an object
as a result of its interaction with another object. So let's look at the three examples here.
We have a tiny man pushing on a massive finger. No idea why but that's stock images for you.
This is a push. There is an interaction between one object and another object. It's a contact
interaction. They're in contact with each other so we can describe that as a force.
Let's look at the magnet below. There's a pull going on here so it's a push or a pull
and there is two objects interacting with each other. Yep that's good. In this case it's non-contact
and we'll discuss what that means later. And finally we have these satellites orbiting the
earth. There's a pull in action there to keep those satellites in orbit. There's two objects
in interaction with each other. The satellite's in the earth and it's non-contact. They're not
touching each other. So we can describe all of these things as forces and now we know what a
force is. We can look at Newton's three laws. The first law, unsurprisingly, is called Newton's
first law. The definition of Newton's first law is here and this is something you'll have
to memorize. An object will remain at rest or continue to move with a constant velocity
unless acted upon by a resultant force. I'd like to really delve into this in a little
bit more detail because there's two key elements here and the first element is remain at rest.
If we consider this football here there will be two forces acted upon this. It'll have the force
of weight and it will have the normal or the reaction force. If you've never heard of these
forces before don't worry we will go over them later. The key to these forces is they are
balanced. The weight force equals the reaction force and that's why the object remains at rest.
When another force comes in, for example this football boot, that external force means that
the object will not remain at rest any longer so Newton's first law does not apply any further.
You may be saying, Charlie that's very simple, I'm bored of this. Well I'm going to keep talking
because there's another element to Newton's first law that's important. Let's look at this
definition again. An object will remain at rest or continue to move with a constant velocity
unless acted upon by a resultant external force. A lot of people think that Newton's first law only
applies if the object is stationary or at rest but that's not true. This rocket here
is moving at a constant velocity. It's moving on a straight line and not changing speed.
That means the forces on this object are balanced and it also undergoes Newton's first law
unless it's acted upon by a resultant external force and in this case we're looking at the
engines being turned on. This will become really important when you tackle exam questions later on.
So when you're remembering Newton's first law don't forget this element of or continue to move
with a constant velocity. It's really important not only just to get full marks when they ask you
to define Newton's first law but also to actually answer the questions. Let's move on to Newton's
second law. Earlier we had an object in Newton's first law and the forces were balanced on either
side so let's just say that's thrust and that's friction. In Newton's first law the value of
thrust would be equal to the value of friction. In Newton's second law that is not true. You can
see here this is Newton's first law. The value of thrust is 100 Newtons and the value of friction
is 100 Newtons so there's no acceleration. That object is undergoing Newton's first law.
As soon as those forces become unbalanced then Newton's second law applies because it causes
acceleration. So if we look at the second situation here we have thrust is equal to
200 Newtons, friction is equal to 100 Newtons. That means there is a resultant force of 100
Newtons towards the right and that resultant force causes an acceleration. Similarly in this third
situation we have 300 Newtons going to the right, 100 Newtons of friction, the resultant force
is 200 Newtons and that resultant force causes an acceleration and the sum of all forces
acting on the object are not equal to zero. I guess a good way of saying Newton's second law
would be the acceleration of a body with constant mass is proportional to the resultant force
applied in the direction of the force. That is such a lot of words but useful for you to put down
in your definition section. You'll know that a graph, a proportional graph, directly proportional graph
has the two quantities that are in direct proportion on either axis. It's a straight line
through zero. If you are considering Newton's second law you would say that force is
proportional to acceleration but if we want to make that into a formula we have to say equals
and there's a constant of proportionality. This is a constant of proportionality and what you find
if you do any form of experiment with Newton's second law is that constant of proportionality
is equal to the mass of the object that is being accelerated. f equals ma and f equals ma
is basically the short way of writing Newton's second law. I wouldn't get too cocky about using
Newton's second law. There are two situations in particular that are quite tricky to work through.
Those situations are when you're dealing with pulleys and the other situation is when you're
dealing with elevators or lifts as we call them in the UK. So for that reason I've put two
separate tutorials below this just giving you some ideas on how to solve Newton's second law
problems when we're looking at pulleys or elevators. On to Newton's third law. If a body A
exerts a force on body B, body B will exert an equal and opposite force on body A.
Let's call earth body A and the moon body B. The earth exerts a force on the moon
and the moon exerts an equal and opposite force on the earth. That's it and you'll find that
there's certain laws that need to be followed to see if we are looking at a Newton's third law
pair and we'll discuss that a little bit later on in this tutorial. For the moment can you head
to your revision note template and in the definition section can you write down Newton's
laws one two and three in your revision note template and also write down the definition
of a force. Pop that in there as well. Download A2 part one knowledge questions and attempt
questions one to eight. That will help you apply all this stuff we've been talking about and makes
you understand it. Next we're moving on to learning objective two which is solve translational
equilibrium problems using Newton's first law and learning objective five draw free body diagrams
and analyze them to find the resultant force on a system in one and two dimensions only. Gosh
well that sounds complicated doesn't it? It's not really don't worry let's move on.
Translational equilibrium is when the resulting force acting on the body must be zero. That's
the definition of translational equilibrium. Now we found before when we were looking at Newton's
first law if the resultant force is zero then the object is at rest or it's traveling at a
constant speed and that's the clue we need when we are looking at exam papers. Exam papers
and examiners in particular always give you a clue when you have to do problems on translational
equilibrium and you can see some of these exam questions here constant speed constant velocity
constant speed constant velocity constant speed steady speed constant velocity. Let's keep going.
Stationary at rest equilibrium the force in one direction equals the force in the other direction.
So in this case thrust and friction thrust is equal to friction if that's 100 Newtons
and that's 100 Newtons then 100 equals 100 we get it right? If something's falling then the weight
is equal to the drag force so if the weight is 50 Newtons the drag force is 50 Newtons
that would be falling at a constant speed therefore it's in translational equilibrium
and that's when you're looking at two forces one goes in one direction the other goes in the other
direction and they're balanced. There is the situation where you might have three forces
and for three forces the following rules apply all horizontal components of force add to zero
and all vertical components of force add to zero. We have three forces here we've got the tension
force of 65 Newtons we've got a force pulling this ball that way that would just be somebody
holding it and we have the force of weight pulling it down there are three forces acting
on this object. Let's look at the horizontal components of force the horizontal in that
direction is 43.5 Newtons and if you were to work out the component of this tension force
in the left hand direction you would find that the horizontal component is 43.5 Newtons
because all horizontal components of force add to zero. Similarly if we look at the vertical
components the vertical component downwards is 48.3 Newtons and if you take the vertical component
of the 65 Newtons and work it out the vertical component would also be 48.3 Newtons so all
vertical components of force add to zero as well all forces cancel. If you find yourself in a
problem where there are three forces in translational equilibrium what you have to do is break it down
into what are the components of forces acting left what are the components of forces acting right
what are the components of forces acted upwards and what are the component forces acting downwards
all the horizontal ones are equal and all the vertical ones are equal. This brings us on to
a bit of feedback from the examiners. The examiners have told us that very few candidates
have the ability to treat a body as a single particle and analyze the forces acting. What
does that mean? Well it means that very few students are able to draw a free body diagram
and a free body diagram is when you look at an object for example this box sliding down a hill
and you turn it into a single point mass with all the force arrows acting from that point
and ensuring that all those force arrows are to scale and at the correct angle. The center of
gravity of this box would be here and then what we'd want to do is just add arrows to that center
of gravity or that point mass to make sure that we're representing the forces correctly in the
right direction and the right length. Here are the rules for free body diagrams and forces questions
when we're looking at translational equilibrium. Look for the phrases constant speed of velocity
equilibrium stationary at rest at that point you know all the forces are balanced
or the resultant force is equal to zero. Draw a free body diagram and this is one of the biggest
mistakes that most students make. If you don't draw a free body diagram you're likely to miss
things out it's really important and finally make sure all forces are equal in all directions.
I think it'd be a good idea now to take you through an example using these rules to show
you how you would apply it in an exam situation. Here we go. Rule number one was to look for
certain phrases in a question to tell you to give you a hint that you are looking to apply
Newton's first law and those phrases were constant speed, constant velocity, steady velocity
at rest equilibrium and so on. So let's go through this question. An athlete trains by
dragging a heavy load across a rough horizontal surface. Here's our athlete here there's a heavy
load there and he's dragging it along and it's a rough horizontal surface. The athlete exerts
a force of magnitude F on the load that's our load there at an angle of 25 degrees to the horizontal.
Once the load is moving at a bing bong steady speed the average horizontal frictional force
acting on the load is 470 newtons. Calculate the average value of F that will enable the load
to move at a bing bong constant speed. Rule number one has been applied. We know that we are dealing
with Newton's first law. Rule number two was to draw a free body diagram. So the load that we're
interested in the mass that will become a point mass is this load here. We'll draw that as a
point. We know that 470 newtons act backwards along the frictional surface as friction.
We know that the athlete exerts a force F in that direction. We don't know the magnitude of it
but we do know that it's at 25 degrees to the horizontal. We also know that this load has
a certain weight. We don't know the value of the weight but we do know a weight exists
and finally we all know that there's a reaction force applying in the opposite direction to weight.
The reaction force won't be equal and opposite to the weight because this athlete is reducing that
reaction force slightly by pulling it at an angle. What we do know is that this object
is moving at a constant speed. So the force the frictional force going backwards is 470 newtons.
That means that the force or left the force going to the right must also be 470 newtons.
If this force were any other value there would be an unbalanced force acting upon the load
and the load would undergo acceleration. We know it doesn't undergo acceleration.
So this must be 470 newtons to balance that 470 newtons. That allows us to create a right
angle triangle with 470 newtons on the adjacent side. The angle is 25 degrees
and the hypotenuse is F. We can then use trigonometry or socatua as some people know
it to work out what the value of H is or the hypotenuse which we also call F.
So let's substitute our values in.
COS 25 equals 470 over F. Therefore F equals 470 divided by COS 25. That gives us a value of
518.59 newtons. If we go back to the question you can see that the data is given to two
significant figures. So our answer should also be given to two significant figures.
So our final answer for F is 520 newtons. Okay back to our notes I'd like you to write
down the definition of translational equilibrium in your revision note template. If you go to the
diagram section I'd like you to draw an example of a free body diagram in the common diagram section
and I'd like you to answer questions 9 to 13 in A2 part one knowledge questions.
Let's look at Newton's third law in a little bit more detail and identify force pairs using
Newton's third law. We already know that Newton's third law is defined as if body A exerts a force
on body B, body B will exert an equal and opposite force on body A. And I mentioned before
that there are Newton's third law pairs all over the world and in the universe because we have an
example here of the earth and the moon. But let's look at the rules for Newton's third law
force pairs. A pair of forces of being Newton's third law will always have
the forces acting on two separate bodies that's rule number one.
Rule number two is both forces have exactly the same type of force.
Rule number three is they will be equal in size. Rule number four is they are opposite in
direction and rule number five is they act in a straight line. If we can look at a force pair
and see all of these five things apply then we're looking at a Newton's third law pair.
Here's an example of a man running. The first rule was are the forces acting on two separate
bodies? Well one force is acting on the foot here and the other force is acting on the earth.
So yes the first rule is a tier two they are acting on two separate bodies.
The second rule was do they both have the same type of force and the force acting on the foot
is friction the force acting on the earth is friction so yes. The third rule was are both
forces equal in size? Yes they are. The fourth rule was are the opposite in direction? Yes they
are. And the fifth rule was do they act in a straight line? Yes they are. So this person
running on the earth is an example of a Newton's third law pair. Let's look at another example.
We have a book resting on a table and the question says do the following pair of forces adhere to
Newton's third law? And the two forces are reaction force and weight of book. I'll tell
you right now this violates rule number two for Newton's third law because we have a reaction
force and a weight force. Those forces are not the same so Newton's third law pair does not
exist here. So let's look at my notes on this. Rule number one was they act on two separate
bodies and there's a book and a table fine. Rule number two was the forces must be the same.
The force on the book is weight but the force on the table is the reaction force. So these two
forces are not the same type of force. However they're both equal in size they're both opposite
and they act in a straight line so we were nearly there but these forces do not adhere
to Newton's third law. Please can you head to your revision note template and write down the
five points or the rules that identify force pairs using Newton's third law. Then answer
question 14 in A2 part one knowledge questions. There are lots of different forces in IB physics
and they largely fall into two different groups contact forces and non-contact forces or field
forces. The IB syllabus specifies all the forces that you need to understand and we'll talk through
them right now. So let's look at contact forces first and contact forces are ones that you come
into contact with. The first one we look at and we've seen a little bit already is the normal
force and sometimes it's called the reaction force. In IB physics it's given the notation
f sub score n. The definition of the normal force is the component of the contact force
acting perpendicular to the surface that counters the body. We've already seen that when we
considered the book resting on the table earlier. You can see that the normal force
is acting perpendicular to the surface in contact and the weight force is causing that
contact force. If we have somebody resting against a wall the normal force is perpendicular
to the hard surface. If we consider a ball rolling down a hill the normal force is perpendicular
to the hard surface. That's the key point for reaction force or the normal force
that it's always acting perpendicular to the surface and contact.
Next we'll look at the frictional force and in IB physics notation is given f sub score f.
The definition is the surface frictional force acting in a direction parallel to the surface
of the plane contact between a body and surface. So you can see this frictional force here with
the box being pushed along the surface. That frictional force is parallel to the surface
of the plane contact and it's in the opposite direction. So this box is moving that way
so the frictional force is moving this way. Look at the car. The car is moving this way
so the frictional force is moving that way and it is in parallel to the contact surface.
There are two different types of friction that you should be aware of.
Static friction and dynamic friction and they're both being given these formulae here. I know you'll
want an extra tutorial on this so I've added an extra tutorial on static and dynamic friction
for you below just to delve into that in a little bit more detail. The next contact force we'll look
at is elastic force and in IB physics it's given the notation f underscore h. The definition of the
elastic force is the elastic force exerted by a material when it is stretched or compressed
and tries to return to its original shape. This is all about Hooke's law is fh is equal to minus kx.
So when you're discussing elastic force you're inevitably going to be looking at Hooke's law.
You've probably seen Hooke's law in relation to a spring where it's being compressed or stretched
and that's where this all comes into play. The next contact force is called viscous drag force
and it is given the notation f underscore d. The definition is the resistive force exerted by a fluid
on an object moving through it. The example we have here is a ball bearing
moving downwards through castor oil as a result of its weight and there's a force acting backwards
resisting its motion which is drag a bit like friction and it's eventually going to balance
out and cause a constant speed here. The key point of this is the viscous drag force is greater in
thicker fluids so if you have a fluid that's got a high viscosity like honey castor oil then
that drag force that viscous drag force is going to be greater. There is a formula
for a small sphere falling through a fluid and this formula for viscous drag force
six pi nu r v where nu is a fluid viscosity and that would be given to you.
R is the radius of the sphere and v is the velocity of the sphere.
You'll be expected to use that equation in exam questions.
And our final contact force is buoyancy force. Buoyancy force is given the notation fb.
The definition is the upward force acting on a body due to the displacement of fluid.
If we look at the iceberg here this iceberg is floating and the reason it's floating is
this volume of seawater here has been displaced by the iceberg. The actual iceberg has taken its
place and that displacement of that seawater causes a buoyancy force upwards and it's governed
by Archimedes principle. The formula for buoyancy force is fb equals rho which is density,
v which is volume and g which is a gravitational field force. Let's now consider non-contact
forces. When we looked at forces at the very beginning we noticed that satellites were in
orbit with the earth, magnets were pulling things towards it but nothing was actually touching
and those things are called non-contact forces or field forces. We're going to look at three in
particular. Gravitational force has the notation f underscore g. Sometimes it's called weight and if
you look in the example of the apple here it would have a weight but if you look at the
earth and the moon then you wouldn't call that weight, you'd call that the gravitational force.
So it really depends on what situation you're looking at. The definition of gravitational
force, and we go into this in much more detail later on in the IB physics course,
is a force that attracts two objects with mass towards each other and the key point here is
all objects with mass exert gravitational forces. The larger the mass the stronger the gravitational
pull. The next non-contact force is electric force. It has the notation f underscore e.
The definition is the push or a pull between charged objects or particles and again we're
going to look at this in much more detail later on in the IB course. The key point here is the
opposites attract. You can see these two charges, positive and negative, they are opposites to each
other so they attract, they pull towards each other. The opposite happens when you have like
charges and this poor little baby's hair is standing on end because every single strand
of this baby's hair has an excess of electrons and an electron doesn't really like another
electron. They repel and that's what's causing this poor little baby's hair to stand on end and
repel from each other. Finally magnetic force which has the notation f underscore m. The
definition of the magnetic force is the force of attraction or repulsion between two objects
due to their magnetic properties and again just like charges like magnetic poles repel
and unlike magnetic poles attract. Let's head to your revision notes. Write down the definition
of any force you didn't know already. Go to the formula section, write down all the
formulae associated with these contact forces and finally go to questions 15 and 16 in A2
part one, knowledge questions and try them. We've got to the end of part one of this massive
topic. Once you've done the work here let's move on to part two. We can now begin part two
of our very long topic A2 forces and momentum and part two looks at momentum. There are five learning
objectives that we're interested in. These learning objectives range from 8 down to 12
in your learning objectives checklist. Without further ado let's start with number eight.
Define linear momentum and understand that it remains constant unless the system is acted upon
by a resultant external force and at the same time we'll look at A2.11, solve problems using
momentum and impulse for collisions and explosions, one-dimensional for SL and two-dimensional for HL.
Okay let's define linear momentum. Linear momentum is defined as the product of mass and velocity of
an object and in fact it's almost always acceptable just to define it as the formula.
Momentum is given the notation p equals mv. You'll notice there's arrows above p and v,
that's just to denote that momentum and velocity are vectors so linear momentum is a vector
quantity. It does matter what direction we look at for momentum. The units of momentum,
you can actually use two different units, you can use kilograms meters per second squared
and that's because the units of mass is kilograms and the units of velocity is
meters per second squared so you put them together and you get kilograms meters per second squared.
But there's also the opportunity to use newton seconds. Why can we use newton seconds? Well let's
consider the formula for force which we know of course has units of newtons, the formula is mA.
So the units of newtons can also be written as kilograms meters per second squared and these
are all SI units, they're all fundamental units. We're nearly at the stage where we have the same
units as momentum but this s to the minus two is an issue. So if we take the units here
and multiply it by s then what we get is kgms to the minus one and that is the equivalent of
newtons seconds. So newton seconds is the same as kilograms meters per second and they can both be
used as units for linear momentum. When an object is traveling along, here's my car,
it's terrible isn't it? It has mass, it has velocity, you can work out what the momentum is,
easy. We're kind of interested more in momentum when we look at things crashing or colliding
or exploding. We're looking at the interaction of this car doing something and that's where
the conservation of momentum comes in. The law of conservation of momentum states that
during any interaction where no external force is at, the total linear momentum is conserved
in any specified direction. So what does that mean? It means the car that we looked at earlier
crashes then the momentum before that crash is the same as the momentum afterwards as long as
there's no external forces acting and that looks mathematically like the total momentum before a
collision is equal to the total momentum after a collision and you can see they're both vector
quantities so direction does matter. The main thing that you'll be asked to do in an IB
physics exam is solve a problem to find out what the velocity of an object is after a collision
or what the total mass of an object is using this idea of the conservation of momentum and
there's a set of five rules I would use to make sure you answer those questions perfectly.
The first rule is the clue that you're using momentum and the conservation of momentum.
The clue is you'll see the words collision, explosion or you might even see the word
momentum which would be the biggest clue. Then you draw a diagram on the left hand side you draw
a diagram of the situation before the collision and on the right hand side you draw a diagram
of the situation after the collision. Number three, rule number three is to choose a direction as
positive. Number four is to apply momentum to each body before and after the collision and number
five is to remember that momentum before equals momentum after. Now does that sound complicated?
Well let me show you an example of me using these five rules and I think it'll make things
a lot simpler for you. Let's go. Rule number one of momentum questions is to look for a clue
that the question is actually about momentum. Obvious words might be momentum in the question,
that would be a hint, but also words like impact, collision, explosion. This question here is about
an air rifle pellet that's fired into a block of waddling clay. The pellet remains inside the clay
so what happens is that the pellet is being fired at a clay block. After it's been fired
the pellet remains inside the clay block and it moves together after the collision. Oh here we go,
here's the word collision. Rule number one has been found. We now know that this question is about
momentum. We're given a set of data here and we were asked to show that the initial speed of
the clay block after the collision is 4.8 meters per second. So rule number two was to draw a
diagram before and after the collision. So I tend to do it in the form of a table. I'll have the word
before here. Oh my writing's dreadful there sorry and after. Before we have a pellet that has a mass
of oh sorry two grams and a velocity of 140 meters per second and that's given in the question.
That is being fired at a stationary mass of clay which has a mass of 56 grams
and a velocity of zero. The after the collision the bullet goes inside the clay so we're now acting
as one mass. That's mass one plus mass two equals 58 grams and we'd like to know how fast it's
traveling. We need to choose a direction as positive and I think in this example it makes
a great amount of sense to choose the right as positive. So anything that moves in that direction
in our example is going to be positive and anything that moves in the other direction
and left direction will be negative. So now we apply the momentum formula for each of them
m1 v1 plus m2 v2 equals m1 plus m2 or mass times velocity for the second one.
The reason we can see there is an equal sign there is because of the conservation of momentum
momentum before or sorry total momentum before equals total momentum afterwards in the absence
of external forces. So we pop in our numbers two times 140 and it's all going in that direction
plus 56 times zero equals 58 times v. So we have 280 equals 58 v, v equals 4.828 meters per second
all the data is given to two significant figures so v equals 4.8 meters per second
and if we go back to the original question we have the we have proved the answer.
Now we've chatted through the definition of linear momentum and we understand what the
conservation of momentum is. Can you note both of them down in your revision note template?
And now I'd like you to go and try questions one to five in A2 part two knowledge questions
and use the rules I've just talked you through. Use them to try and answer those questions properly.
In the last section we talked about momentum and how we can analyze the momentum before a collision
and the momentum after a collision. In this section I'm interested in what's happening
during the collision. What's happening at that point where the momentum has been changed from
one point to another and that concept revolves around something called impulse. Learning objectives
9 10 and 11 all deal with the concept of impulse. As I said before we're thinking about momentum
changing and we noticed earlier in the exam questions that we're looking for the words
collision explosion maybe even the word momentum but during this collision or during the
explosion a force must act on an object during a very short period of time and if we take this
example here before the collision we have a ball heading towards a wall and after the collision
the ball moves away from the wall it's got a different speed but it's got the same mass
because it's the same ball. At the point of collision here there must have been a force
acting on the ball over a short period of time that caused that change in momentum
and it's in this point of the causing of the change in momentum that I'm interested in.
But before we go into defining impulse and the point of change in momentum I'd like to
take us right back to Newton's second law because we've already previously defined Newton's second
law as F equals ma and we've said you know force is proportional to acceleration and the constant
of proportionality is mass. That's a more popular known version of Newton's second law but Newton
didn't actually define his second law like that. Newton defined his second law in these words he said
the rate of change of momentum of a body is equal to the resultant force acting on the body.
Rate of change of momentum. If you were to represent that in maths you'd say rate of change of momentum
rate of change means divide by time. How quickly is something changing with respect to time?
So the rate of change of momentum is equal to the resultant force acting on the body. So actually
Newton's second law in a mathematical form is F equals delta p over delta t.
Let's try and break that down a bit because delta p just means the final momentum subtracts
the initial momentum. So the final momentum is mv the initial momentum is mu and this delta t
keep that the way it is. The mass is the same so we can take that out and what we're left with
is m brackets v minus u over t and of course from a1 kinematics you would know that v minus
u over t is equal to a. So F equals ma. What is very clear though is when a force acts upon a
body over a period of time a change of momentum occurs. That's what I'm talking about here. When
a force acts on a body over a short period of time a change in momentum occurs. The momentum
that way is different to the momentum that way and that is the foundation of impulse.
Impulse is defined as the change in momentum of an object and it's given the symbol j
and j has the formula the change of momentum we can start with m delta v but it's also got
the formula F delta t. How do we get that? Well let's go back to what we saw earlier.
We saw this which brought us to m delta v over delta t so we've got F equals m delta v over delta t.
So Ft equals m delta v and both of those things are equal to j. They are both the formula for
impulse. The units of impulse are kilograms meters per second which is the same as momentum
which makes sense because that's the quantities in momentum or Newton's seconds which makes sense
because the units of F times t is n s. It's also a vector quantity. So the key to remembering about
impulse is that there's two expressions we can use to find the impulse of a collision or a change
of momentum. Why does this matter? Well impulse you see it everywhere in real life once you understand
it you see it everywhere. Let's think about a car crashing so we've got this car heads towards the
wall it's got mass m and velocity v so it's got an initial momentum hits the wall okay sadly and
its final momentum is equal to zero. There's a change in momentum there. That change in momentum
is constant because it starts off with a constant mass and a constant velocity and it ends up with
quantities that aren't changed either. The change in momentum this value here is constant.
What that means is if you can increase the time taken for any collision then you must be able to
decrease the force that is applied during that collision and all of these situations here
represent that concept of impulse. A seat belt what a seat belt does is it stretches
and by stretching it increases the time taken for you to stop which means the force applied
to you decreases and it doesn't hurt as much. A crumple zone. A crumple zone increases the
time taken because it crumples so it takes a longer time for the car to stop which means the
force on the car lessens. If you jump and bend your knees by bending your knees you're increasing
the time it takes to stop and you're decreasing the force on your knees thus saving your joints
and a tennis racket what you actually want to do is increase the force on that ball on your
tennis racket so you want to decrease the amount of time it takes to change the momentum of the
ball which means you want a very tight string so you want tight strings on your tennis racket to
increase the force that the ball is released with. So impulse begins to allow us to explain
real life situations. If I can just direct your attention up here for the moment I think it's
pretty easy to use this formula there's not much in it and it should be relatively simple for you
that is it's simple if the force is constant it's simple because it's just a formula you pop in the
numbers. Here's a question for you though let's go back to these situations here. Do you think
there's a constant force on the seat belt as it's slowing you down? Do you think there's a
constant force on the crumple zone as the car's stopping? Do you think there's a constant force
on your knees or on the ball as it changes momentum? No that force changes over time and the
way it changes over time tends to look like this graph here it starts off with a small force gets
to a maximum force and then as it changes direction and leaves the force decreases again.
So it's not always useful to use this equation when the force is not constant then we have to
look to a graph to help us work out any quantities to do with impulse and the key for you to remember
here is the area under a force time graph is equal to impulse. So if you are presented with a
force time graph you know you're dealing with impulse you know you're dealing with change
in momentum. Please can you get your revision note template out and in the definition section
write down the definition of impulse. I would like you to go to the common
formulae section or the other notes section and write down the link between Newton's second
law and momentum. Also write down the formula for impulse. Go to the common graph section
and draw an annotated force time graph and then finally do questions 6 to 9 and a2 part 2 of the
momentum section and we want to understand what an elastic collision is and an inelastic collision
is and explosion of course and this section really delves back into what examiners have said in the
past. Examiners have said that very few candidates seemed to know what was meant by an elastic
collision. Now that is not going to be you. Let's look at inelastic and elastic collisions.
We know from previously that momentum is conserved in all collisions assuming no
external forces apply. We can make lots of calculations with that simple knowledge. However
if you consider a collision kinetic energy is not conserved because when a collision happens it's
going to lose energy. It's going to lose sound energy and heat energy and if that happens
then this collision is inelastic. If it loses kinetic energy during a collision then it's
inelastic. I've got news for you most collisions and most explosions are inelastic. An elastic collision
is one where kinetic energy is conserved so if you take the kinetic energy of the ball here
before the collision down here and you take the kinetic energy of the ball here after the collision
these two kinetic energies would be exactly the same. Can you imagine this happening in real life?
Not particularly, no. Energy is lost in most collisions and explosions. So examples where
it might happen would be in atomic collisions. Nevertheless this is assessed in your IB physics
exam and you do need to know the difference between elastic and inelastic collisions
and you do have to make the calculations. So with that in mind go to your revision note template,
write down a definition of an elastic and an elastic collision and then answers questions 10
and 11 and A2 part 2 of your knowledge questions. We've finished the momentum section of A2 forces
and momentum. Next section is looking at circular motion. We're doing that let's go. The final part
of A2 forces and momentum looks at circular motion and it's the final four learning objectives
of our learning objectives checklist. Let's start off with oh quite a lot of them number 13, 14 and
15. Velocity changes. I would like to consider a satellite orbiting the earth.
At v1 that speed is perhaps let's say 500 meters per second and at v2
the speed is the same it's 500 meters per second. It's a constant speed but the velocity is changing.
The velocity is changing because at v1 the direction is that way and for v2 the direction
is that way. If a velocity is changing then the object is accelerating and that's because
acceleration is defined as the rate of change of velocity and velocity clearly changes.
With that knowledge we can actually do a little bit of vector subtraction to find out
what the direction of acceleration is for an object that's undergoing circular motion.
We know that acceleration is defined as the rate of change of velocity so we would like to find the
change in velocity of this satellite that's shown around the earth and the change in
velocity means the final velocity minus the initial velocity and remember in A1 I taught
you the trick on how to subtract vectors it's the final velocity plus minus the initial velocity.
So let's take that down to here. We want to subtract v1 here from v2 here and to do that we add
v2 plus minus v1. Minus v1 now v1 isn't going in that direction so minus v1 is going in that
direction. We're going to add vectors v2 and minus v1 tip to tail and that will give you
the resultant vector in this direction here. So the vector direction of the change in velocity
or the acceleration is in this direction here. No matter what stage you do that around
the circular motion you always have the change in velocity vector directed towards the center.
The acceleration vector is always directed towards the center no matter where you do
this simple vector subtraction and feedback from the examiners and pass have said
candidates were unable to use a vector diagram to explain the need for a centripetal force
in circular motion. Where's force coming into it? We've only really been talking about
velocity and acceleration. Do you remember that if there's an acceleration there must be a force
applied to it? So if there's an acceleration towards the center of the circle there must
be a force directed towards the center of the circle and that force is called centripetal force.
Head to your revision note template and in the explain section or the other note section
explain how an object traveling at a steady speed can be accelerating in your notes and
I would draw the change in velocity vector in your common diagrams section.
On to the last but very large learning objective to do with circular motion and it's understand
and solve problems involving centripetal force, centripetal acceleration, period frequency,
angular displacement, linear speed and angular velocity. For you, quite a lot to get through.
Let's start very simply. We really want to understand radians and why they're used in physics.
Okay, radians are often used because they're multiples of pi
which is a natural number and it's a natural unit for trigonometric functions.
Physicists prefer radians. It links everything in much better and the angle in radians is defined
as the arc length divided by the radius. So you can see the arc length is here
divided by the radius which is here and if we compare it with degrees, degrees is based
on dividing a circle into 360 equal parts whereas radians is only based on the radius of the circle.
It is important you understand that both degrees and radians can be used and understand that
90 degrees is equal to pi over 2 radians, 180 degrees is equal to pi radians,
360 degrees is equal to 2 pi radians and so on. You should be able to convert between the two.
I think it's now time to define angular displacement. Angle displacement is defined as the angle in
radians or degrees through which a point has been rotated about a specific axis. You can see on the
diagram here the angular displacement is the angle through which a point has been rotated
and it's to do with the arc length and the radius. Let's have a look at linear velocity. Let's have
a think about how fast something is moving around a circle. Linear velocity or tangential velocity
is the velocity of a point on a rotating object. So if we think about a satellite orbiting earth
like we did had earlier then the tangential velocity is this. Okay that's a terrible diagram
but there we go and the formula for linear velocity is 2 pi r over t. You will recognize
2 pi r as their circumference and the circumference is equal to a distance.
So the linear velocity is equal to distance over time which is 2 pi r over t. R is of course the
radius of the point and the units of linear velocity are meters per second also written
like this. If you consider a wheel and we have two points, a red and a blue point,
those points are placed on the wheel. The red point has a smaller radius than the blue point
and if we consider the equation v equals 2 pi r over t then the red point has a smaller radius
which means it has a smaller linear velocity than the blue point. So when you're considering
linear velocity the radius may be smaller for something which means that the linear velocity
is smaller. However let's now look at angular velocity. Angular velocity is given the symbol
omega. Angular velocity is a rate of change of angular displacement with respect to time
and if you remember earlier we had angular displacement as this angle here. So angular
velocity is how quickly does this angle change? It's the rate of change of angular displacement.
Theta is the angular displacement, t is the time taken and the units of angular velocity
is rads per second or radians per second. Looks like that. If you consider this red point and
the blue point on the wheel again, the rate at which the angular displacement changes
for the red dot and the blue dot is exactly the same. So even though v red has a smaller
linear speed and angular velocity and we can do that using this relationship v equals omega r.
Let's remind ourselves of the equations. Linear speed is equal to v equals 2 pi over t. The units
are meters per second. Angular velocity is omega equals theta over t and the units are radians
per second and we can link linear speed and angular velocity using this relationship.
Do you remember when we were discussing the satellite going around in a circle
and we analyzed the velocity vectors to find the change in velocity and what we found was
that the acceleration was always directed towards the center of the circle. We found that out
earlier but we didn't have a formula to tell you exactly what magnitude of that acceleration
was. Now we have a formula. The centripetal acceleration is a equals v squared over r
and it has meters per second squared units just like in linear motion. But we also know
that v equals omega r and if we substitute that into here we end up with a range of different
expressions for centripetal acceleration. Similarly Newton's second law states that
the resultant force equals mass times acceleration in the direction of the force. So if we have
acceleration towards the center we have force towards the center and the force is equal to
a. That means we can add f equals m a to our acceleration equations and we end up with these
equations for centripetal force. The force is always measured in Newton's. If an object
is in circular motion there's a force towards the center of the circular motion then that
force has to have a name. We talked about forces earlier. We talked about all sorts of different
forces. This force has to have a name. It can't just be a centripetal force. It has to
have a force that's causing this centripetal force and one of the skills of IB physics is identifying
the type of force. Now if we're looking at a satellite going round earth the type of
force that's causing that centripetal motion is a gravitational force. If we're looking at
a ball being swung around somebody's head on a string then this force here is tension.
Head to your revision notes and in your revision note template include equations involving centripetal
force, acceleration, period, frequency, basically all the formulae we've just written down.
Get them in your notes and then do questions one to seven in a two part three of the knowledge
questions. We have completed a two forces and momentum. It's been our journey. You now
understand all the concepts involved in this topic and the next step for you on the tribe
success path is to activate the application. Let's start applying all our knowledge
into exam style questions. Let's move on. Let's go.